Now, I'm aware that I have this
interesting problem that the audience of
this course is a very mixed audience.
Some of you are engineers that are
looking to come into the world of vibe
coding and agentic engineering and get
pretty hardcore with it. And some of you
are are not so technical, might be
coming in new to this and want to use
vibe coding as a way to generate code.
So, I'm just going to take a minute to
talk mostly to the people that that are
coming new into this to level set. So,
for people that are already pros, please
put me on 2x. Just zip through this
part. I'm also I've taken a few slides
from my ML ops track just just as a
quick briefing for people new to this.
We've been doing stuff this week that's
been using front-end code and I realized
you might not even have the sort of con
context of okay so I you know I'm sure
you've heard terms like front end and
backend a lot but how does that actually
fit together? We're about to make a
project with both a front end and a back
end. What does that mean? How does it
work? Let me quickly explain. So, put
simply, the projects we'll be working on
in this course are what they call web
applications, meaning that you use a
browser to access them. And it's very
common for web applications to have
what's called a front end and a backend
as two parts of the technology. And
obviously, the front end is the stuff
that runs in the users's web browser. It
runs within Chrome or Safari or
Microsoft Edge or whatever. And it's
typically got some combination of HTML
which is the web page, CSS, the
stylesheets which controls the
appearance and then JavaScript code
running in the browser that controls the
kind of interactivity and the
functionality that runs in the browser
in the client on the front end. And then
obviously the back end as you probably
know is something which is running on a
server. It's perhaps the thing that
served up the the web page in the first
place. the HTML and CSS and JavaScript
that your browser connected to it to get
it, but also your browser can can reach
and and send messages to the server in
order to run some business logic that
could be accessing a database. It might
be calling an LLM and it might be uh
other other APIs you might be calling
out to and you might also have your
secrets, your passwords perhaps in a MV
file on your back end on your server.
That's the back end. And in terms of the
projects we've done this week, the day
one kind of teaser was just all front
end. The the uh then the camb board we
did on day three that was also all front
end. Uh all JavaScript served up to the
front end. And then what we did
yesterday, it did actually have a back
end, but it was also in JavaScript. It
was that that was the part that was
calling open router. So you can have
frontends and backends in JavaScript.
What we're going to do today is going to
have a front end in JavaScript and a
backend in Python which is the most
common backend programming language for
people working with LLMs because we're
again going to build an application
using agents that itself is going to
call an LLM. All right, so that's that's
front end versus backend. And to state
the obvious, the way that they are
connected is through these things called
APIs. I'm sure you know this, but the
front end makes an API call to the back
end and that's how it retrieves
information it needs to to populate the
front end or because the user has
pressed a button that is like a submit
button and that is calling an API back
is coming results. Uh and so that that
is the the the way that front end and
backend collaborate to to solve a
business problem. And all of you you
pros there are like uh thinking of all
the ways I'm oversimplifying. So feel
free to explain it better than me in the
Udemy Q&A if you wish. And just very
quickly to dig into the front end, it's
not particularly a big part of this
course and it's something which which I
imagine most of you are probably more
backend ccentric. Uh and some of you
might be front- end devs in which case
you're going to hate me for
oversimplifying. But just to give you
the lay of the land so you know roughly
what's going on, you can have websites
that are built with basic vanilla HTML,
which is what we did in day one. HTML,
JavaScript, CSS, maybe the JavaScript
uses some of the libraries like jQuery
that are really simple, low-level
libraries. Not much to it. But over
time, frameworks came along which sort
of allowed you to build user interfaces
out of components that could update
themselves. And React is one of the the
really big ones. Vue, Angular, Velt,
these are all these are all popular
front-end frameworks that you see a lot.
And typically the whole of the front end
will load as as like one request and
then different components will make
different API calls to repopulate
themselves. And when it works that way
it's known as a single page app and spa
and that's very very common and they're
sometimes written in JavaScript they're
sometimes written in the typed version
TypeScript and uh both both both
variants exist and then there are
frameworks like Nex.js JS that's
actually created by by the company
Versel that that is great for
deployments. Uh Nex.js is something
which sort of packages together a bunch
of related concerns like how to route
through web pages, how to fetch data,
how to render things on either the the
client or to render them on the server.
All of that is packaged together into
Nex.js. So it's a sort of higher level
application framework. That is what
we've been using for the last few days
and we'll use it again today uh for the
front end and it's it's it's something
that's great and easy. Now I'm a bit of
a horror with with React and Nex.js. I
can do it. I find it really really
difficult and so for me using LLMs using
coding agents has been a lifesaver
because they are really really strong at
this. Actually having said that I will
just give a caveat to that. I do also
see that whilst LMS are very strong at
this, they often create websites that
look very similar, web apps that they
look a bit a bit like slop, they they
have the same kind of look, sometimes
with that purple hue, but you get very
familiar with seeing the kind of three
icons and that that very standard LM
generated look. And one of the ways that
that great UX people, you UXUI people
really stand out is is knowing how best
to organize and communicate information
to make an impact on your user for best
outcomes. And that's that's where you
can still play a role. So even though
when the LLM generates the front end, it
can look it can look really great to
start with, you need to go back and push
on it to make sure you get something
that is unique and interesting and good
for your users and so on. That's where
you can add the value. Okay. Hopefully
the front end people aren't furious with
me for oversimplifying. Remember you can
always you can always add to the
conversation. I am now going to do one
more bit of foundational explanation
again taken from my MLOps course which
is to introduce Docker that we're going
to be using which is also a great part
of the toolkit for someone who is vibe
coding. So Docker is something again I
imagine 60 to 70% of you know it back to
front. Just a few of you I'm sure
everyone's heard of it. Not sure what it
is. Let me quickly demystify then we'll
install it and then we will get going
with today's project. So the easiest way
to describe Docker is that Docker gives
you a computer within your computer. It
gives you this kind of ring fenced set
of resources that's running on your box
in a way that is isolated from the
outside world. If you if you know about
virtual machines, it's a sort of
lightweight alternative to virtual
machines which are very similar. That in
a nutshell is what Docker is. And so the
the sort of the so what the reason that
people love Docker is first of all that
it isolates everything inside this
little world so that you can't damage
the outside world. And obviously that's
something that's that's important for
for agentic coding. It's also super
portable that you could build it once
and have it working in one place and
then just deploy it somewhere and have
it working over there and and so on.
There are some footnotes there. It's,
you know, if only life were that easy,
but still it's better than many of the
alternatives. It's pretty good for just
taking a one it built once and move it
somewhere else and it usually just
works. And there are three concepts to
be aware of with Docker with some
vocabulary that you get used to in the
Docker world. First of all, there's
something called a Docker file. The
Docker file, it's a file and it's like a
recipe. It's like a set of instructions
that describes how you will install
stuff and configure stuff on this box
within the box. That's what the Docker
file is. And the Docker file is used to
build an image. A Docker image. A Docker
image is like a snapshot of the world.
It's like a it's like a particular kind
of blueprint for your uh for for your
box within a box that you'll be able to
then use to create lots of these boxes.
That is what the image is, the snapshot.
It's it's created from a Docker file and
it's ready ready for prime time. And so
what is prime time? Prime time is what's
called a Docker container. A Docker
container is made from a Docker image.
And the container is an actual live
environment, a live box within your box.
And it's created from an image. And of
course, you probably get the idea. You
could have one image that could create
many of these containers. Each container
is a little box within your box. And you
can have many of them and they all run
in this very isolated way. And that's
that's the basics on Docker. And of
course there's it's a there's so much we
could say about Docker. I just wanted to
sort of lay lay the foundations there.
And for the pros, you know this stuff
already. And never fear, we'll be using
these a lot more in the next few weeks
and we're going to get much more
advanced on this stuff. Okay. And we're
now for those that don't already have
Docker on your system, we're going to go
and install Docker so that you've got
it. And so you go to a website, first of
all, a hard to find website. It's
docker.com. Go to docker.com
and this should come up for you. And you
can see there's there's lots of stuff
here. And the thing that you want is
called Docker Desktop. That's what
you're going to install. And check this
out. This is a download Docker Desktop
button. And it's got the different
versions that you might want to
download. And you should download it and
run it and check out the course
resources because I'm going to add in if
there's anything that people come across
that they're not expecting. But
basically, you accept all the defaults.
Don't do anything special. On a PC, it's
probably going to prompt you to do it in
a way that involves WSL. And I advise
you to do that. Yes, just stick with the
defaults. Do it its way. There'll be a
bunch of stuff to install. Do what it
says. Go through all of that. Everything
should get installed. It's possible you
need to restart your computer to get
your path variable updated, but at the
end of it, you should have Docker
Desktop running. And when you have
Docker Desktop running installed, you
should be able to open up see something
like this Docker Desktop screen that
I've got here. It's like an app. And on
the left here, you'll see containers and
images. And this shows you, it should be
blank for you. You won't have any. I
have a bunch again, the blueprints, the
things that have been created from a
Docker file and are ready for prime
time. Containers is when they've
actually been created. They are being
run. They are alive. They are little
worlds. And of course, there's lots of
other stuff. You can have volumes which
is like sort of ring fenced uh space
storage that could be used by your
containers. So there's lots of detail of
course but that's the basics. That's all
you need to know for now because now
we're going to go and build a project.